We left off with the idea that the return of any stock, i,
在上个视频中 我们提到任何股票 i 的收益率
can be decomposed into the returns of factors times
可以分解为因子的收益率
the stocks exposures to those factors plus an unexplained portion.
乘以相对于这些因子的暴露度加上无法解释的部分
But wait, this is looking a lot like multiple regression.
但这看起来很像多元回归
What's the difference?
二者有什么区别？
Well, regression is one tool you might use to build a factor model.
回归是构建因子模型的一种工具
Also, in a factor model,
此外 在因子模型中
the independent variables or factor returns are usually things we think are there,
自变量或因子收益率通常是我们认为存在的项
but have an influence that we can't measure directly.
但是我们无法直接衡量它们产生的影响
These are called unobserved or latent random variables.
称为未观察到或潜在随机变量
We may need to take other steps to produce
我们可能需要采取其他步骤生成这些时间序列
these time series before we can run a multiple regression.
然后才能运行多元回归
For example, what if we think
例如 如果我们认为
a company's size has something to do with the performance of its stock price?
公司的规模与股价业绩有关 会怎样？
Maybe, smaller companies stock prices produced higher returns?
也许小型公司的股价收益率更高
Okay. That seems reasonable,
Ok似乎有道理
so let's do a regression.
我们通过回归方法检验下
But hang on, what data do we have?
但是我们有哪些数据？
We have time series of returns for several stocks.
我们有多支股票的收益率时间序列
You've seen those data before.
你之前见过这些数据
Okay. So size, how do we measure that?
Ok如何衡量规模？
Lets say, we're specifically thinking that market cap is the metric of interests.
假设市值是我们感兴趣的指标
Market cap is the market value of a publicly traded companies outstanding shares.
市值是指上市公司的已发行股票的市值
It's the share price multiplied by the number of shares outstanding.
等于股价乘以已发行股数
So, we'd have market cap for every company in our universe for every day,
我们需要股票池中每个公司每天的市值
because it changes over time.
因为市值会逐渐变化
That sounds like the data could be organized in a table or a matrix.
看来数据可以整理成表格或矩阵
But to create a single factor return time-series,
但是要创建单个因子收益率时间序列
we're looking for a single time-series of values that
我们需要寻找能代表多支股票的规模因子影响的
represents the effect of the size factor across stocks.
单个值时间序列
Do you see the challenge we're facing?
你注意到我们面临的挑战了吗？
How do we create a single time series that represents our idea
如何找到这样的单个时间序列
that small-cap companies generally outperform large-cap companies.
它能够代表小股盘通常会跑赢大股盘这个结论？
Moreover, how do we quantify this effect on the returns of a whole set of stocks?
此外 如何量化对所有股票收益率的这种影响？
A latent variable is something like this,
潜在变量是一种模糊的变量
something nebulous that we want to represent as a time series like a normal variable,
我们希望像正常变量一样将其表示为时间序列
but it's hard to directly measure.
但是很难直接衡量
What we do in this case to create a single time series for our factor,
为了创建单个因子时间序列
is we create a theoretical portfolio.
我们将创建一个理论投资组合
This portfolio long small caps and shorts large-caps every day.
这个投资组合每天都做多小股盘并做空大股盘
The time series we seek is the portfolio's daily return.
我们要计算的时间序列是投资组合的每日收益率
This is how we quantify our idea that small caps should outperform
我们通过这种方式表示小股盘会跑赢大股盘这个结论
large-caps and generate a single time series to represent this idea.
并生成表示这种结论的单个时间序列